<figures><fig id="f1"><image>ncomms1133-f1.jpg</image><caption>(a) Feeding behaviour of P. iwasakii. (b) A skull specimen (dorsal view) of P. iwasakii, exhibiting half a dozen more teeth on the right side of mandibles than on the left before hatching. Bars: 10 mm.</caption></fig><fig id="f2"><image>ncomms1133-f2.jpg</image><caption>Each bar indicates the proportion of successful survival of sinistral S. perversa and dextral S. mercatoria (left), and of sinistral variant and dextral wild-type B. similaris (right) against predation by P. iwasakii (means across four snakes±s.e.; n=10 for each snake). S indicates attempts on sinistrals and D on dextrals.</caption></fig><fig id="f3"><image>ncomms1133-f3.jpg</image><caption>Each bar indicates the proportion of genera composed of sinistral species in a 10-mm shell diameter interval ((a), flat snails; (b), tall snails; (c), total) showing the outcome of statistical analyses that used individual shell sizes as a numerical variable. Closed and open bars indicate the proportions within and outside the range of pareatid snakes, respectively. The number above each bar indicates the total number of genera included in each size range.</caption></fig><fig id="f4"><image>ncomms1133-f4.jpg</image><caption>Each bar indicates the proportion of genera composed of sinistral (a) flat-shelled and (b) tall-shelled species. Closed and open bars indicate the proportions within and outside the range of pareatid snakes, respectively. Family names are denoted by the following abbreviations; Ariophantidae (Ar), Bradybaenidae (Br), Camaenidae (Ca), Chondrinidae (Ch), Corillidae (Co), Enidae (En), Dyakidae (Dy), Pupillidae (Pu), Subulinidae (Su), Tornatellinidae (To) and Vertiginidae (Ve). Families distributed across both ranges are shown. The number above each bar indicates the number of genera included in each family.</caption></fig><fig id="f5"><image>ncomms1133-f5.jpg</image><caption>(a) Geographical distributions of sinistral (red) and dextral (blue) snails and pareatid snakes (orange) in East Asia. (b) Phylogenetic relationships of sinistral (red) and dextral (blue) snails based on maximum likelihood analysis of the combined CO1, ITS and ETS sequence data. Several clades containing only dextral species are compressed in blue (see Supplementary Fig. S1 for details). Specific names are listed in Supplementary Data 2. The numbers on branches indicate MP and ML bootstrap values, followed by Bayesian posterior probabilities (&lt;50% not shown). Shells of some representative species are shown.</caption></fig></figures>